Guide to the Edward James Parrish papers and Japanese photograph albums, 1888-1926
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Edward James Parrish papers and Japanese photograph albums 1888-1926
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Parrish, Edward James, 1846-1920
9.2 Linear Feet Approx. 535 Items
Tobacco manufacturer, resident of Durham, North Carolina, and Tokyo, Japan.
The papers of Edward James Parrish primarily consist of business and personal correspondence (chiefly 1900-1921) of Parrish and of his wife, Rosa Bryan Parrish. There are also various bills, a notebook on tobacco trade in China and Japan (1894-1900), letter books (1900-1904), and a Bible owned by Parrish, and a scrapbook and postcard album created by Rosa Parrish. Parrish was a representative of the American Tobacco Company. The early papers, including turn-of-the-century photo albums, relate to the Murai family and to Murai Brothers, a Tokyo cigarette manufacturing company of which Parrish was the first vice-president. Two of the photographs albums date from the late 19th century and were owned by Kichibei Murai; they contain photographs of his residences and of banks, mines, oil fields, farms and tobacco factories in which he had an interest. Also included are photographs of the Parrish's travels in China, and Mrs. Parrish's reminiscences and impressions of her life in Japan.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
However, all photographic materials may only be accessed in consultation with a reference archivist as they may be fragile.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Edward James Parrish papers and Japanese photograph albums were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as gifts, purchases, and transfers from 1941 to 1987.
Biographical Note
Edward J. Parrish (1846-1920) and Rosa Bryan Parrish (1852-1927) were residents of Durham, N.C., and traveled to Japan and China in connection with Parrish's work as a representative for American Tobacco and the British-American Tobacco Company. During his successful operations in Japan establishing a tobacco market, Parrish had conferred upon him by the Emperor of Japan the "Third Order of Honor," and was decorated with the "Medal of Sacred Treasure." Parrish was born in Pound Hill, in what was then Orange County, N.C., in 1846. He attended Trinity College, and served for a short time in Company "K," 4th N.C. Cavalry, in the last year of the Civil War. He married Rosa Bryan in 1870 and moved to Durham around 1871 to establish a grocery and confectionery store. He then became a tobacco auctioneer, and built the first brick tobacco warehouse in Durham in 1879 (later destroyed by fire). The Parrish family's primary home in Durham before moving to Japan in 1898 was a large Second Empire structure on Main and Dillard; upon his early retirement around 1904, he remodeled "Lochmoor," on North Roxboro Road (both residences were later demolished).
Source: USGenWeb Archives, online biography by Leonard Wilson, first published in 1916.
Collection Overview
The papers of Edward Parrish primarily consist of business and personal correspondence (chiefly 1900-1921) of Parrish and of his wife, Rosa Bryan Parrish. Parrish was connected to the American Tobacco Company. The early papers, including turn-of-the-century photo albums, relate to the Murai family and to Murai Brothers, a Tokyo cigarette manufacturing company of which Parrish was the first vice-president. Two of the photographs albums were owned by Kichibei Murai, and contain photographs of his residences and of banks, mines, oil fields, farms and tobacco factories in which he had an interest. Also included are photographs of travels in China.
Other papers include personal letters from Parrish written during his stay at Hot Springs, Arkansas; bills for purchases made by Rosa (Bryan) Parrish; letters from Jones Fuller, her attorney, concerning the collection of Parrish's insurance policies after his death; letter books containing Parrish's letters from Durham, N.C. and Tokyo, 1900-1905; a notebook on tobacco trade with China and Japan, 1894-1900; a Bible owned by Parrish; and a scrapbook and postcard album created by Rosa Parrish. Among the undated material are Mrs. Parrish's reminiscences and impressions of her life in Japan.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Murai family
Parrish, Edward James, 1846-1920
Parrish, Rosa Bryan
American Tobacco Company
Murai Kyodai Shokai, Tokyo
Cigarette industry -- East Asia
Cigarette industry -- Japan -- Tokyo
Tobacco industry -- North Carolina -- Durham
Industries -- North Carolina -- Durham
China -- Description and travel
China -- Pictorial works
Durham (N.C.) -- History
Japan -- Description and travel
Japan -- Pictorial works
Glass plate negatives
Letter books
Photographs
Photograph albums
Postcards
Scrapbooks
Related Material
Richard Henry Gregory papers, 1905-1910 (employee of British-American Tobacco in China)
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
James Augustus Thomas Papers, circa 1900-1985 (tobacco merchant involved in early trade with China)
Contents of Collection
- Edward James Parrish papers and Japanese photographs albums, 1894-1926, (23 boxes)
  - Correspondence, 1888-1919 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence (Box 2)
  - Legal papers (Box 2)
  - Papers, 1894-1926 (Box 3)
  - Volumes: Murai albums I and II, late 19th century (Box 3)
  - Notebook on tobacco trade, 39 pp., 1894-1900 (Box 3)
  - Financial papers (Box 4)
  - Clippings (Box 4)
  - Printed materials (Box 4)
  - Photographs on glass plates (Box 5)
  - Memorabilia (Box 6)
  - Genealogy (Box 6)
  - Photographs, induding Parrish's Durham residences (Lochmoor) (Box 6)
  - Tobacco miscellany (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous Volumes (Box 8)
  - Volumes: Albums from Japan (Box 9)
  - Volumes: Albums from Japan (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous volumes (Box 11)
  - Volumes: Albums from Japan (Box 12)
  - Volumes (Box 13)
  - Volumes: Scrapbook of Rosa Parrish (Box 14)
  - Popular cookbook
  - Volumes: Rosa Parrish postcard album, 47 pp. (Box 15)
    Contains postcards collected by Mrs. Parrish from Japan, China, Germany, Ireland, England, France, New Zealand, and the U.S. in the early part of the 20th century.
  - Volumes: Albums from Japan (Box 16)
  - Volumes: Albums from Japan with China photos (Box 17)
  - Volumes: Albums from Japan (Box 18)
  - Volumes: Albums from Japan (Box 19)
  - Volumes: Albums from Japan (Box 20)
  - Volumes: Albums from Japan (Box 21)
  - Volumes: Albums from Japan (Box 22)
  - Volumes: Albums from Japan (Box 23)
  - Realty sale poster (Opaperfolder 1)
  - Albums of pictures of Japanese houses, photos (Opaperfolder 2)
  - Letter book, Durham, N.C. and Tokyo, Japan, 1900 Jan. 17-Sept. 25 (Volume L:5686)
  - Letter book, Durham, N.C. and Tokyo, Japan, 1900 Oct. 4-1901 Aug. 27 (Volume L:5687)
  - Letter book, Durham, N.C. and Tokyo, Japan, 1901, Aug. 28-1902 Aug. 4 (Volume F:5688)
  - Letter book, Durham, N.C. and Tokyo, Japan, 1902 June 24-1904 Oct. 18 (Volume L:5689)
  - Letter book, Durham, N.C. and Tokyo, Japan, 1902 Aug. 11-1903 Dec. 16 (Volume F:5690)
  - Letter book, Durham, N.C. and Tokyo, Japan, 1904 Sept. 26-Dec. 2 (Volume L:5691)